Gail Mary Killian and Stephen Desroches sound recordings 14439340
Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gail Mary Killian and Stephen Desroches sound recordings
1970-2003
Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Killian, Gail Mary, 1953-1988
DesRoches, Stephen K. (Stephen Killian), 1974-
14439340
OHAC
23 audiocassettes
Conditions Governing Access
Access: Open
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series. The series are based on the provenance of the interviews. Within each series, recordings are arranged chronologically.
Related Materials
The item "Diary and notebook of Gail Mary Killian" (GDP / 165) is found in the Great Diary Project of the Archives of the Bishopgate Institute, London, United Kingdom
Biographical / Historical
Gail Mary Killian (March 30, 1953-August 11, 1988) was a recording enthusiast with Down syndrome who lived in Eastern Massachusetts. She received a tape recorder for her birthday in 1970. Recording her birthday each year became an annual tradition from 1970-1984. She also recorded daily life and visits from friends and neighbors, including her best friend Denise. Killian was an avid music fan, who enjoyed rock and roll and traditional Polish music. Her interest in documenting her life and the world around her extended to other media as well. She retained every greeting card that she ever received, kept a diary, and recorded every movie and television show that she saw by annotating TV Guide.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen Desroches has worked as a journalist in Provincetown, MA on Cape Cod. He received a degree from Columbia University's Graduate School of Journalism in 2002. Desroches has worked to preserve and document his family's history, both by interviewing older relatives and by stewarding the tapes and diary of his aunt Gail Mary Killian until their donation to archives.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the collection's interviews were taken by Gail Mary Killian and document her life in the 1970s-1980s as a woman living with Down syndrome in Eastern Massachusetts. Killian recorded her birthday starting in 1970, and many recordings capture the conversations that took place at these celebrations, which were attended by family members and neighbors. Topics discussed at these parties include music-related gifts received by Killian; rock music and Polish folk music; television shows and movies; employment opportunities for people with disabilities in the region; work at the United States Postal Service (her father's employer); and happenings in their local community. The family also sings together, both in English and Polish. Also included are recordings made by Killian during her daily life. Killian was an avid music fan, and she records thoughts on rock bands such as the Beatles, Journey, and Van Halen. Portions of the local New Bedford, MA radio program "Polish Happy Hour" are captured on tape.
Scope and Contents
The collection also contains three oral history interviews by Killian's nephew Stephen Desroches, who donated all tapes. One interview is with Desroches' grandfather Stanley Killian, taken in 1991. This interview documents Killian's experiences in World War II. A second interview was taken in 2003 with three relatives of Desroches: Stanley Killian (grandfather), Eugene Killian (great-uncle), and Helen Killian (grandmother). This interview covers the experiences of their immigrant parents, the Great Depression, World War II, and their thoughts on politics and social issues at the time of the interview. Desroches also interviews Schuyler "Ted" Meyer, the police chief of Provincetown, MA, about Meyer's experiences in law enforcement in an artistic Cape Cod town.
Custodial History
Stephen Desroches was immediate source of acquisition for all tapes. They were gifted to the Oral History Archives at Columbia in 2018. Desroches is the nephew of Gail Mary Killian. Eighteen tapes were created by Killian and five were created by Desroches
Down syndrome -- Social aspects.; Polish Americans -- Social life and customs.; Rock music -- Social aspects; World War, 1939-1945; Depressions -- 1929; Police -- Interviews.; Provincetown (Mass.); Taunton (Mass.); New Bedford (Mass.); Fall River (Mass.); Sound recordings; Oral histories (literary works); Interviews; Beatles; Journey (Musical group)
- Gail Mary Killian sound recordings, 1971-1984; 18 audiocassettes
  - New tape recorder / Rusty, 1970; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Scope and Contents
    Gail Mary Killian discusses favorite television shows, her dog Rusty, and her favorite books. She also discusses the Beatles at length with a friend.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's birthday (1971), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's birthday celebration. Discussions include Killian receiving a Beatles album as a gift, and Killian teaching older guests the slang term "bread" meaning money.
  - Tape labeled "Not Clear", circa 1971-1972; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording of teaching the baby to talk and a conversation about employment opportunities for people with disabilities in Taunton and Fall River, Massachusetts.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's 19th birthday, 1972; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's nineteenth birthday. Highlights include Killian's baby niece saying new words and adults trying to get the baby to make a peace sign.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's birthday (1973), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's birthday celebration. There is a conversation about work for the United States Postal Service, as Killian's father and neighbor worked for the USPS. Guests sing "Happy Birthday." There is also a conversation about polka music and dancing, both of which were popular in her neighborhood, which was a Polish enclave.
  - Helen Singing, 1973; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Gail Mary Killian records her mother Helen snoring (the tape's title is a play on the snoring as "singing") while the Boston Red Sox game plays on radio. Recording also includes playing Partridge Family records and singing along with the baby.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's birthday (Birthday 21; 1974), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's twenty-first birthday celebration. Recording is comprised of conversation and singing in Polish.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's birthday (Birthday1974; 1974), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's twenty-first birthday celebration. Recoding includes discussion of "Tonight Show."
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's birthday (Birthday 1976), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's twenty-third birthday celebration.
  - Various artists / Talkin' and Radio, circa 1977; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording of Gail Mary Killian and friend listening to Foreigner and Journey and talking about which rock stars they think are cute.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's 24th birthday (24 years, 1977), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording of Gail Mary Killian's twenty-fourth birthday celebration. The recording includes a discussion of "Charlie's Angels" and Farrah Fawcett. Killian receives tickets to see Andy Williams, Jim Nabors, and Bobby Vinton. The family sings Vinton's song "Melody of Love" and Polish folk songs.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's birthday (1980), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
  - Journey captured, 1981; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Gail Mary Killian speaks with a friend while listening to the new Journey and Van Halen albums. The recording also captures a segment of "Polish Happy Hour," a local news and music program for the Polish community broadcast on a New Bedford, Massachusetts radio station.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's birthday (Gail's birthday, 1982), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's birthday celebration. Topics discussed include a neighbor's granddaughter being accepted to Yale University, increased Portuguese immigration to Taunton, and talk of a new video arcade in town that has Ms. Pac-Man and Space Invaders.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's 30th birthday (Carol's house, 1983), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording of a surprise party at Carol's house for Gail Mary Killian.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's 30th birthday (Party at home, 1983), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's thirtieth birthday celebration. Topics discussed include a mean priest, labor issues at the United States Postal Service, changes in tourism patterns on Cape Cod, and a substitute teacher in the town who is blind. Killian receives records by the Go Go's and Toto.
  - Recording of Gail Mary Killian's 31st birthday (Happy birthday 31st, 1984), 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    Recording documents Gail Mary Killian's thirty-first birthday celebration.
  - New Bedford polka program, undated; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
- Stephen Desroches oral history interviews, 1991-2003; 5 audiocassettes
  - Oral history interview with Stanley Killian, 1991; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    This interview with Stanley Killian (1922-1999) was conducted by his grandson Stephen Desroches. The inteview was taken when Desroches was sixteen for a high school assignment in which students were to ask older family members about World War II. The tape incidentally contains a recording of Desroches narrating the movie Jaws II.
  - Oral history interview with Stanley Killian, Eugene Killian, and Helen Killian, September 27, September 29, and October 3, 1999; 3 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    This interview with Stanley Killian (1922-1999), Eugene Killian (1920-2012), and Helen Killian (1922-2015) was conducted by Stephen Desroches. Stanley and Helen were Desroches' grandparents, and Eugene was his great-uncle. At the time, Stanley had terminal brain cancer, and when Desroches visited he would record conversations of all present. Topics discussed include the Great Depression, World War II, and the experiences of their immigrant parents. The Killians also share their views on contemporary politics, including gun control, healthcare, the Clinton/Lewinsky scandal, and the Democratic and Republican Parties. They also discuss social issues such as divorce and couples living together before marriage.
  - Oral history interview with Schuyler "Ted" Meyer, 2003; 1 audiocassettes (Box OHAC C9)
    This interview with Schuyler "Ted" Meyer was conducted by Stephen Desroches in 2003. Meyer was Chief of Police in Provincetown, Massachusetts, a small community at the tip of Cape Cod known for its art colony, eccentricity, and large LGBTQ community. The interview covers life in Provincetown, LGBTQ issues, and his previous experience as police chief in Richardson, Texas. Richardson had a large Muslim population, and Meyer discusses issues around keeping the Muslim community safe in the aftermath of the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks.